# Nicolás Cuesta Quintero

# **Financial Engineer**

#### Contact

Medellín, Colombia (+57) 312 - 796 - 5598 nicolaicuesta@hotmail.com LinkedIn (click here) Personal Site (click here)

### **Key Skills**

R / C++ Excel / VBA Power BI / SSAS /SSRS Computational Finance Quantitative Finance

## Activities and Interests

Financial Research Capital Markets BI & Data Science

#### **Profile**

Financial Engineer and candidate to a master's in Computational Science. Located in Medellín, Colombia, he considers himself as a methodic worker, Finance passionate and R enthusiast, always trying to tackle financial problems from a quantitative and computational perspective. His most recent experience has let him improve his programming skills, learn about Business Intelligence and Analytics while diving deep down into real estate and alternative investments Finance.

### **Experience**

July 2021—Current

Developer IV (BI/Power BI) • RealPage Inc. • Medellín, Colombia

Developing the analytics for a platform that help limited and general partners in real estate equity deals to consolidate their financial and operational information. This job let him understand the industry conventions and what the market players were looking for to generate alpha. It was diving deep into the data needs that industry participants had; from **investment level reports** to calculate internal rate of returns on all cash contributions and distributions of their investment entities, **portfolio level dashboards** that assessed regional or tenant industry exposure, and **property level tear sheets** letting them track tenant receivables and credit loss exposure.

March 2020—June 2021

Developer III (BI/Power BI) • RealPage Inc. • Medellín, Colombia

As part of the data and visualizations team, he has played an important role in all major components of modern BI solutions, including the **data architectures** design and implementation, the **data integration** process to ensure the correct warehousing of the data, the construction and development of **data cubes** for modeling purposes and, more important, the creation of **dashboards and reports** that thoroughly narrate the story hidden by vast amounts of data. This experience has been crucial to impel his capacity of joining the best of two worlds: The *Data Management* domain and the *Computational Finance* field.

May 2019—March 2020

Business Analyst • RealPage Inc. • Medellín, Colombia

He had the opportunity to help Business Intelligence teams in four crucial points: **knowledge management**, by allowing developers to better understand the business logic behind their datasets; **requirements management**, by translating clients' needs from a financial language to a technical one; **quality assurance**, creating business rules that final solutions must satisfy; and **data science**, by leveraging on R software to transform, organize and validate data, create new visualizations and models to understand data, and communicate business-oriented narratives.

August 2018—May 2019

Jr. Business Analyst • RealPage Inc. • Medellín, Colombia

He joined the valuations team as a Business Analyst to update quarterly valuations of properties all around the US. This experience let him understand better the common practices in Real Estate valuation, by applying the Discounted Cash Flow (DCF) methodology for offices and medical offices, as well as retail and mixed-use properties. He also had the opportunity to value storages and industrial properties and developed a tool for measuring changes in valuations due to capital markets.

December 2017—August 2019

SAP Engineer • ifb Group • Medellín, Colombia

This opportunity let him understand the way in which Financial Institutions are organized from the Back Office, and their relationship with new information technologies. He worked on Compliance for Foreign Investment Funds by creating regulatory reports for UCITS' and CPO's. Moreover, he was trained on SAP Bank Analyzer and SAP HANA. With the first one, he had the responsibility of verifying cash flow generation for consumer credits and corporate debt issues and keeping track of Amortized Cost calculations.

June 2017—December 2017

Intern • Isagén SA ESP • Medellín, Colombia

Financial risks intern who worked in three main projects: market risk models for short-term liquidity investments, implement an external CAMELS model to assess credit risk of foreign banks and developing a liquidity risk index.

# **Education**

### December 2021 (Tentative)

MSc. Computational and Scientific Modeling • Universidad de Medellín • Medellín, Colombia

#### March 2018

Financial Engineer • Universidad de Medellín • Medellín, Colombia